{"tossups": [{"question": "<b>John Gerin performed an autopsy on this man, whose body was dissolved with sulfuric acid after authorities decided that quicklime wouldn\u2019t work fast enough. This man used the</b> <b>alias \u201cFred (+)</b> <b>Nieman\u201d during a meeting in the house of the editor of the</b><em><b> Free Society</b></em><b>,</b> <b>Abraham Isaak; at that meeting, this man sought to meet with Emma (*)</b> Goldman. Gaetano Bresci inspired this man, who concealed an Iver Johnson revolver at the Temple of Music during the Pan-American Exposition in Buffalo. For the points, name this anarchist who, in 1901, assassinated William McKinley.", "answer": "Leon Frank<b> Czolgosz</b> ([chol-gosh], but be very, very lenient with pronounciation)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In the aftermath of this event, the UK broke diplomatic ties with the country in which it took place because Dora Bloch, a 75-year-old woman, went missing from her hospital.</b> <b>Jean-Jacques Maimoni was (+)</b> <b>accidentally killed during his event, which involved the</b> <b>killing of Wilfried B\u00a8ose and 6 other hijackers. Yonathan (*)</b> Netanyahu died in this event, which was carried out by the IDF to end a hostage situation that had been supported by Idi Amin. For the points, name this July 4, 1976 Israeli rescue mission that took place at an airport in Uganda.", "answer": "Operation<b> Entebbe</b> (or Operation<b> Thunderbolt</b>; accept Operation<b> Jonathan</b> before mentioned; accept descriptions of the raid on<b> Entebbe</b> Airport; prompt on descriptions of the end of the 1976 hostage crisis that don\u2019t mention<b> Entebbe</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This ruler\u2019s overthrow came after the execution of the Zhang brothers. Manuals on torture were compiled by this ruler\u2019s secret police under the order of Lai Junchen, who</b> <b>was (+)</b> <b>executed after falsely implicating the crown prince. This patron of Buddhism</b> <b>constructed a Dayun Temple in every province upon ascending the throne. This founder of the (*)</b> Zhou Dynasty served as regent for the Emperors Zhongzhong and Ruizhong, her sons. The Tang Dynasty was interrupted by two decades of rule under, for the points, what sole empress of China?", "answer": "Empress<b> Wu</b> Zetian (accept<b> Wu</b> Zhao or<b> Wu</b> Chao) Page 1", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s friendship with John Ridge sparked an interest in Cherokee linguistics that ultimately led him to publish</b><em><b> A Table of Indian Languages of the United States</b></em><b>. With John Russell Bartlett, this man co-founded the oldest (+) anthropological society in the US. He became ambassador to France in 1816, two years after he helped negotiate the Treaty of (*) </b>Ghent. Unlike Alexander Hamilton, this man was staunchly opposed to large national debt. New York University was founded by, for the points, what Swiss-American who was the longest-serving Secretary of the Treasury?", "answer": "(Abraham Alfonse) Albert<b> Gallatin</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Vincent Og\u00b4e [oh-zhay] called for certain rights granted by this document to be extended</b> <b>to men of color. This 17-article document\u2019s lack of women\u2019s (+)</b> <b>rights prompted the</b> <b>creation of a similar document two years later by Olympe de Gouges [oh-lamp de goozh]. This document\u2019s first article only approved of \u201csocial distinctions\u201d that were in the interest of the (*)</b> \u201ccommon good.\u201d The National Assembly passed and the Marquis de Lafayette helped write, for the points, what 1789 French document inspired by the Declaration of Independence?", "answer": "<b> Declaration of the Rights of Man</b> and of the Citizen (accept<b> D\u00b4eclaration des droits de l\u2019homme</b> et du citoyen) (8) <b>Blacksmiths from this empire erected an iron pillar that has resisted corrosion to the</b> <b>present day. The Ajanta cave complex was designed during the reign of this empire, which</b> <b>was visited by the Chinese (+)</b> <b>monk Faxian and whose rulers inclued Vikramaditya.</b><em><b> The</b></em> <b>monk Faxian and whose rulers inclued Vikramaditya.</b><em><b> The</b></em> <em><b>Recognition of Sakuntala</b></em><b> was written by (*)</b> <em><b>Recognition of Sakuntala</b></em><b> was written by (*)</b> Kalidasa during the rule of, for the points, what empire that ruled India from the third to fifth centuries AD, well after the earlier Mauryan Empire, and was ruled by Samudra and Chandra? ANSWER:<b> Gupta</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This country was the site of one battle in which Hitler infamously ordered his SS troops to remove their cuff insignias after the failure of Operation Spring Awakening near Lake</b> <b>Balaton. This country, which was occupied during Operation (+)</b> <b>Margarethe, faced a</b> <b>Margarethe, faced a</b> <b>one-hundred day siege of its capital centered around Castle Hill. After Dome (*)</b> <b>one-hundred day siege of its capital centered around Castle Hill. After Dome (*)</b> Sztojay [doh-may stoy-aye] was replaced as prime minister by Geza Lakatos [LAH-kuh-tosh] in this country, Otto Skorzeny executed Operation Panzerfaust to install the pro-Nazi Arrow Cross party. For the points, name this country led in World War II by Miklos Horthy.", "answer": "<b> Hungary</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This city\u2019s rapidly-developing Left Bank area is centered around the Bayterek Tower, which evokes the legend of a golden egg on top of the tree of life. In this city, Norman Foster</b> <b>designed the (+)</b> <b>Khan Shatyr, an entertainment center consisting of a giant transparent</b> <b>tent that is the largest in the world. Expo 2017 will be held in this city on the Ishim River. It was renamed (*)</b> Tselinograd in 1961, shortly after it became an administrative center of the Virgin Lands Campaign. In 1997, Nursultan Nazarbayev moved his country\u2019s capital from Almaty to this planned city. For the points, name this capital of Kazakhstan.", "answer": "<b> Astana</b> (accept<b> Tselinograd</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>A meeting at this location was partially organized by Francis Preston Blair and was an unsuccessful attempt to resolve a promise made in the \u201cTo Whom it May Concern\u201d letter.</b> <b>A battle fought at this location was instigated when (+)</b> <b>Catesby ap Roger Jones decided</b> <b>to finish off the crippled ship</b><em><b> Minnesota</b></em><b>. A conference at this location on (*)</b> board the<em> River</em> <em>Queen</em> failed to broker a peace deal between Alexander Stephens and Abraham Lincoln. For the points, name this site where the<em> Merrimack</em> and the<em> Monitor</em> fought to a duel in 1862, a body of water on the Virginia coast.", "answer": "<b> Hampton Roads</b> (accept Battle of<b> Hampton Roads</b>; accept<b> Hampton Roads</b> Conference; do not prompt on Chesapeake Bay)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man supposedly protected the group \u201cLos Extraditables\u201d by working with M-19 to burn documents within the Palace of Justice. After the assassination of presidential</b> <b>hopeful Luis Carlos Garlan, authorities forced this rival of Los (+)</b> <b>Pepes to live in his</b> <b>private \u201cprison,\u201d Las Catedral. This financier of Atl\u00b4etico Nacional was killed by the Search Bloc (*)</b> police unit in 1993, ending his Medellin-based empire. Wagner Moura portrays this man in the Netflix series<em> Narcos</em>. For the points, name this Colombian \u201cking of Cocaine,\u201d believed to be the richest criminal in history.", "answer": "Pablo<b> Escobar</b> Page 3", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>These people killed Hophni and Phinehas in battle; the news of their deaths shocked Eli so much that he fell from his chair, broke his neck, and died. These people took the Ark of the Covenant following their (+) victory at the aforementioned Battle at Ebenezer. These people worshiped at the Temple of (*) </b> Dagon, which was toppled by a man who lost his sight and strength due to the guile of a woman of this ethnicity. Goliath and Delilah were members of, for the points, what ethnic group often in conflict with the Israelites of the Old Testament?", "answer": "<b> Philistine</b>s", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b>Two queens of this country were the only women to have the</b><em><b> khutbah</b></em><b> declared in their name. The rise of the Sulayhid dynasty forced Zabid\u2019s sons to flee from this country to Dahlak. A king of this country threw the Christians of (+) Najran into burning ditches and committed suicide by riding a horse into the sea. Dhu Nuwas ruled this country\u2019s Himyarite Kingdom, which fell to the (*) </b> Aksum from Ethiopia.<em> Coffea arabica</em> was a common good sold in this country\u2019s city of Mocha. For the points, name this birthplace of Osama bin Laden, a country north of the Gulf of Aden whose capital is Sana\u2019a.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Yemen</b> (accept al-Jumhuriyah al-<b>Yamaniyah</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>700 of these people who operated in Chalcidice [chal-kih-dih-kee] were named Brasidians after their commander. Thucydides wrote of an instance in which these people</b> <b>were massacred at Cape (+)</b> <b>Taenarus by Lacedaemonians. An earthquake prompted a</b> <b>revolt of these people that coincided with the Third (*)</b> Messinian War, and these people were egged on to another revolt by Pausanias, a general of a rival city. These people could become neodamodes [\u201dneo\u201d-dam-oh-dees] after a period of service as hoplites. For the points, name these Spartan slaves.", "answer": "<b> helot</b>s (prompt on (Spartan) slaves before mentioned; do not prompt on Spartans) Page 4", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>Wilhelm F\u00a8urtwangler conducted a 1951 performance of this work that re-opened the Bayreuth Festival. A part of this work was used as a compromise anthem for a United Team of (+) East and West Germany at several Olympic Games. Its premiere was conducted by both Michael Umlauf and its composer, and Charles (*)</b> Rosen called this work\u2019s final movement a \u201csymphony-within-a-symphony.\u201d That final movement, also the anthem of the EU, sets a text that begins \u201cO, Freunde, nicht diese T\u00a8one!\u201d and was written by Friedrich Schiller. The \u201cOde To Joy\u201d is found in, for the points, what final symphony of Ludwig van Beethoven?", "answer": "Ludwig van<b> Beethoven\u2019s Symphony</b> Number<b> 9</b> in D minor, opus 125 (or<b> Choral</b> Symphony;\u201cBeethoven\u201d and \u201csymphony\u201d not necessary after they are mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>Three years before this event, a man nicknamed the \u201cOld Marshal\u201d was assassinated. Wellington Koo accompanied members of a commission sent to investigate this event. That</b> <b>commission was appointed by the (+)</b> <b>League of Nations and was named after Victor (*)</b> Bulwer-Lytton. Kanji Ishiwara helped plan this event, which resulted in the passage of the Stimson Doctrine and involved detonating dynamite near a railway line in Shenyang. For the points, name this 1931 incident that the Japanese used to justify their invasion of Manchuria.", "answer": "<b> Mukden</b> Incident of 1931 (accept<b> Manchurian</b> Incident of 1931 until \u201cManchuria\u201d is read; accept answers like the invasion of<b> Manchuria</b> until \u201cKanji\u201d is read and prompt afterward)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>The main character of a play in this genre disguises himself as Mr. Courtage at a ball as part of a scheme to make his tiresome lover jealous of his many loves. A play in this genre includes a back and forth dialogue specifying a (+) marriage contract in its Proviso Scene. Sir Fopling Flutter appears in a play in this genre, George (*)</b> Etherege\u2019s<em> The Man of Mode</em>. A play in this genre is about the courtship of Mirabell and Millamant. William Congreve\u2019s<em> The Way of the</em> <em>World</em> was an example of, for the points, what literary works produced in England to entertain after the ascent of Charles II to the throne?", "answer": "<b> Restoration Comedy</b> (prompt on partial answers, including Restoration drama)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Drama"}, {"question": "<b>A force sent to take this city was struck by a cholera epidemic at Calamity Bay. During a battle for this city, Francois Canrobert\u2019s men successfully resisted an attack across the</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Tchernaya River. Fortifications protecting this city at the Great Redan and Malakoff</b> <b>Tchernaya River. Fortifications protecting this city at the Great Redan and Malakoff</b> <b>Redoubt were raided for their (*)</b> <b>Redoubt were raided for their (*)</b> guns that, according to legend, were melted into Victoria Cross awards. The Battle of Balaclava, at which the Charge of the Light Brigade took place, was part of the siege of this city. For the points, name this home of the Russian Black Sea fleet that fell to a siege during the Crimean War.", "answer": "(Siege of)<b> Sevastopol</b> Page 5", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Numerous Hispanic residents of Colorado\u2019s San Luis Valley with breast cancer were found to have ancestors affected by one of these actions after genetic testing revealed</b> <b>mutations in the BRCA1 gene. Another action of this type was reversed in (+)</b> <b>1657 and</b> <b>had forced its affected members to wear a yellow patch. Ximenes</b> <b>[hi-MEN-ez] de (*)</b> Cisneros oversaw one action of this type, while another was made official in a 1290 edict by Edward I. One of these actions affected those who refused to become<em> conversos</em>. For the points, name this discriminatory action carried out by Ferdinand and Isabella\u2019s Alhambra decree.", "answer": "<b> expel</b>ling<b> Jews</b> (accept anything related to<b> forcing Jews to leave</b> Spain and/or England; prompt on partial answers like \u201cdiscrimination against Jews\u201d or \u201cexpelling people\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This ship was originally called the</b><em><b> Sir William Hardy</b></em><b>, though it was later renamed after a literary passage noting \u201cthe world is sick and dying, the people will rise up.\u201d While</b> <b>docked in Marsden Wharf, this ship was infiltrated by Alain (+)</b> <b>Tonel. While attempting</b> <b>Tonel. While attempting</b> <b>to retrieve his camera from this ship, the photographer Fernando Pereira (*)</b> <b>to retrieve his camera from this ship, the photographer Fernando Pereira (*)</b> died. Defense Minister Charles Hernu resigned shortly after authorizing Operation Satanique, in which this ship was destroyed while en route to Moruroa for a nuclear protest. Fran\u00b8cois Mitterand ordered the bombing of, for the points, what Greenpeace ship?", "answer": "<b> Rainbow Warrior</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Philip Sheridan once said \u201cI will not divide my forces to protect\u201d this entity. Ephraim Francis Baldwin constructed various locales along this entity\u2019s Metropolitan Branch. Rifle</b> <b>barrels were converted into boiler tubes by Peter Cooper when designing the (+)</b> <em><b>Tom</b></em> <em><b>Thumb</b></em><b>, which was tested on this railroad. Construction of this railroad began with the intent of creating a competitor to the (*)</b> Erie Canal, and it later became absorbed by the nearby Pennsylvania Railroad. For the points, name this early railroad that originated in Maryland but, unlike other railroads featured in<em> Monopoly</em>, did not serve Atlantic City.", "answer": "<b> Baltimore and Ohio</b> Railroad (or<b> B and O</b> Railroad) Page 6", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A team from this country featured Chester Williams and was led by Fran\u00b8cois Pienaar to a victory in its Rugby World Cup debut in 1995. This country is home to the 2009 world</b> <b>champion in the women\u2019s 800 meter run, (+)</b> <b>Caster Semenya, who was then forced to</b> <b>Caster Semenya, who was then forced to</b> <b>undergo sex verification. An athlete from this country nicknamed (*)</b> <b>undergo sex verification. An athlete from this country nicknamed (*)</b> \u201cBlade Runner\u201d was found guilty of culpable homicide in the death of his girlfriend Reeva Steenkamp. For the points, name this home country of double-amputee Oscar Pistorius, whose Springboks were boycotted out of international competition during Apartheid.", "answer": "Republic of<b> South Africa</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>A terror incident in this city prompted Turkish radio reporter Melih Uzunyol to have a heart attack while attempting to reach the scene. This city\u2019s Otherside Lounge, as well as a</b> <b>suburban clinic and targets in (+)</b> <b>Birmingham, were attacked for providing \u201cabortion on</b> <b>demand,\u201d according to Eric Rudolph, who also used an ALICE military (*)</b> backpack stuffed with pipe bombs for an attack initially blamed on Richard Jewell. For the points, name this city whose Centennial Park was bombed during the 1996 Summer Olympics.", "answer": "<b> Atlanta</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>The</b><em><b> HMS Columbine</b></em><b> brought the first dispatches reporting this event to Nova Scotia. Daniel Martin was an African-American victim of this event, which led to the execution of</b> <b>Jenkin Ratford. (+)</b> <b>Salusbury Humphreys was the leader of the aggressors in this event,</b> <b>who fired a broadside round that was only responded to by a single shot before captain James (*)</b> Barron surrendered; shortly after, four sailors who deserted from the Royal Navy were seized. For the points, name this 1807 incident of impressment that enraged the Jefferson administration.", "answer": "<b> Chesapeake-Leopard</b> Affair (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>George Beadle invited this scientist to Stanford from Cold Spring Harbor in 1944 to study the chromosomes of</b><em><b> Neurospora crassa</b></em><b>, a bread mold. This scientist, whose most</b> <b>famous discovery was made after studying the (+)</b> <b>Dissociator and Activator gene loci,</b> <b>stopped publishing data in 1953 in response to unjust skepticism. In 1983, this scientist won an (*)</b> unshared Nobel Prize in Medicine for developing the idea of \u201ccontrolling elements\u201d resulting from her study of the variation in color of maize. For the points, name this American biologist who discovered transposons, or \u201cjumping genes.\u201d", "answer": "Barbara<b> McClintock</b>", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This woman helped pay off the mortgage of a friend named Samuel Hill using money from sales of a print titled \u201cI sell the shadow to support the substance.\u201d This woman moved</b> <b>to Northampton, Massachusetts in the (+)</b> <b>1840s and gave a speech there introducing the</b> <b>hymn \u201cIt was Early in the Morning.\u201d Protests against her speech at the Mob Convention led her to proclaim \u201cyou (*)</b> can\u2019t stop us neither;\u201d that speech occurred two years after a convention, organized in Akron, Ohio, where she repeatedly asked a heated question. For the points, name this African-American activist and orator who asked \u201cAin\u2019t I a Woman?\u201d", "answer": "Sojourner<b> Truth</b> (accept Isabella (\u201dBell\u201d)<b> Baumfree</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This composer took Arcangelo Corelli as a model for his twelve Opus 6 concerti grossi, the ninth of which borrows from his organ concerto \u201cThe Cuckoo and the Nightingale.\u201d A</b> <b>sinfonia for two (+)</b> <b>oboes and strings is often excerpted from his oratorio</b><em><b> Solomon</b></em><b>. This</b> <b>composer of \u201cThe Arrival of the (*)</b> Queen of Sheba\u201d wrote a largo al siciliana entitled \u201cLa Paix\u201dfor an outdoor celebration of the Treaty of Aix-La-Chapelle, and he also wrote three suites for a barge concert held by George II on the Thames. For the points, name this composer of<em> Music for the Royal</em> <em>Fireworks</em> and<em> Water Music</em>.", "answer": "George Friedrich<b> Handel</b> Page 8", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>This \u201cuniqueness\u201d of this historical event is discussed in Yehuda Bauer\u2019s \u201cAgainst Mystification.\u201d The \u201cintentionalist\u201d versus \u201cfunctionalist\u201d debate regarding this</b> <b>historical event was first developed by (+)</b> <b>Karl Schleunes [shloy-ness]. Daniel</b> <b>Goldhagen\u2019s book about this event\u2019s \u201cWilling Executioners\u201d built upon Christopher Browning\u2019s suggestion that its (*) </b> perpetrators were \u201cOrdinary Men.\u201d During this event, Theodor Eicke ordered the installation of signs reading \u201cArbeit Macht Frei,\u201d or \u201cWork sets you free.\u201d For the points, name this genocide committed by Nazi Germany during World War II.", "answer": "the<b> Holocaust</b> (or<b> Shoah</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The central portion of this region is characterized by a \u201cridge and slough\u201d landscape, and the prehistoric Mud Lake Canal was built here. The Calusa people once lived in this</b> <b>region, which is bordered on the southwest by the (+)</b> <b>region, which is bordered on the southwest by the (+)</b> <b>Ten Thousand Islands. Marjory</b> <b>Stoneman Douglas fought for the (*)</b> preservation of this region, which was used as an isolated preservation of this region, which was used as an isolated refuge by a couple hundred Native Americans after their defeat in the Third Seminole War. Big Cypress National Preserve and a namesake national park are both part of, for the points, what \u201criver of grass,\u201d a large wetlands in south Florida?", "answer": "The<b> Everglades</b> (prompt on Florida before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}], "bonuses": []}